<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The character of a trulie vertuous and pious woman as it hath been acted by Mistris Margaret Dungan (vvife to Doctor Arnold Boate) in the constant course of her whole life, which she finished at Paris, 17 Aprilis 1651.</title>
            <author>Boate, Arnold, 1600?-1653?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 97 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28492</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3369</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7222</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11897794</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11897794</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50564</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28492)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50564)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 55:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The character of a trulie vertuous and pious woman as it hath been acted by Mistris Margaret Dungan (vvife to Doctor Arnold Boate) in the constant course of her whole life, which she finished at Paris, 17 Aprilis 1651.</title>
                  <author>Boate, Arnold, 1600?-1653?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 169, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ste. Maucroy for the authour,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Paris :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Boate, Margaret, 1625-1651.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50564:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50564:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHARACTER OF A TRVLIE VERTVOVS AND PIOVS VVOMAN, AS IT HATH BEEN ACTED BY MISTRIS MARGARET DVNGAN, (VVIFE TO DOCTOR ARNOLD BOATE,) In the conſtant courſe of her Whole life, Which she finished at Paris 17. Aprilis 1651.</p>
            <p>PARIS, Printed by STE. MAVCROY for the Authour, 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:50564:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50564:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER IN GOD THOMAS SINSERF, <hi>Lord Bishop Gallovvay.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ay it pleaſe your Lordship,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>Having perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually before my eyes the aymable and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable qualities of my moſt lovelie and moſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved conſort, of vvhom it pleaſed God latelie to deprive me in the prime
<pb facs="tcp:50564:3"/> of her age (to my unſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable grief, and irrepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſcomfort) and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving found ſome conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in reducing in vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting part of vvhat my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie did ſuggeſt unto me of her, for to ſerve me inſteed of a pourtrait, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vvhich I might often paſſe my vieuvv, thereby in ſome ſort to mitigate the exceſſe of my tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting ſadnes, much better than others in the like caſe uſe to doe vvith leſſe livelie and more cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreall
<pb facs="tcp:50564:3"/> repreſentations: I thought good, vvhat I had ſo ſet dovvn at firſt vvith no other intention, than to remaine vvith myſelfe, and to ſerve o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelie for mine ovvn uſe and conſolation, to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish the ſame unto the vvorld; partlie for to acquit vvhat is due to her vertues, deſerving a farre ſtatelier monument; and principallie for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage and edification of others; hoping that her example may ſerve
<pb facs="tcp:50564:4"/> as a povverfull motif, vvhereby many vvilbe ſtirred up to the practiſe of true vertue and pietie, in the ſame manner as theſe lines (free from all amplifications and rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toricall ornaments, and conſiſting of a bare and plaine narration vvithout all artifice) vvill hold forth to have been done by her. And as all thoſe, vvho have knovvn her, can beare me vvitneſſe, that I have ſaid nothing her, but the naKed
<pb facs="tcp:50564:4"/> truth; ſo in particular your Lordship, vvho ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving lodged vvith us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame roof, and come to the ſame board vvith us, for the ſpace of vvell neere three yeares, have ſeen in her conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation all thoſe qualities verified, vvhich here I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late of her: vvhich hath incouraged me, to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate theſe lines unto your Lordship, thereby to put them paſt all contradic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vvith ſuch, as have not at all been acquainted
<pb facs="tcp:50564:5"/> vvith her, and vvho upon my bare record might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceive, that my pen had not been ſo much guided by unbiaſſed truth, as by an over-favourable and pre-occupated affection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as ſome paſſages of this treatiſe vvill receive ſome light by the knovvledge of the accident that hath taken her avvay, and of the manner that it made an end of her; it vvill be good to give a compendious relation of the ſame, before I come to the maine matter.
<pb facs="tcp:50564:5"/> Having been married to me at Dublin on chriſtmas day in the yeare of our Lord 1642. and brought me three children (the youngeſt vvhere-of, beeing a girle, borne here in Paris on the 13. of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 1646. is onelie alive) she miſcarried laſt yeare on the 27. of April, vvithout anie evident cauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and having conceived again about the 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 14. of Auguſt, she vvent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on happilie till the firſt of March, vvithout anie other acommoditie, than that she vvas exceſſive big, more than
<pb facs="tcp:50564:6"/> vvith anie former child she had been, verie un-able to vvalke or ſtirre, and ſubject to frequent faintings; for vvhich laſt accident having been let blood in the arme on the 19. of November, she vvas ſome vveeks the better for it. For the reſt, she had her health vvonderfull vvell and a farre better appetite, than she had had vvith anie of her former children; the vvhich did ſo fill her veines, as it cauſed the aforeſaid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive bignes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and nature beeing overburdened vvith
<pb facs="tcp:50564:6"/> blood, diſcharged itſelfe on the firſt of March in the eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, of a ſuddain, and vvithout anie the leaſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding commotion of mind or bodie, of part of it, in that impetuous manner, as in the space of leſſe than halfe an houre she loſt more than tvvo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and hauing continued to looſe ſome more blood for the space of an houre longer, and begun to bleed afresh the next morning, she had nine ounces of blood dravv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e from her out of her right arme; vvhich preſentlie
<pb facs="tcp:50564:7"/> stayed her bleeding. But she had another fit the 13. of March, though nothing ſo copious as the firſt; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> third on the 22. of the ſame month, much more moderate yet, and ſuch vvas alſo the fourth, vvhich came on the firſt of April. The tenth of April she had a fifth shed much vvhat of the ſame quantitie as the ſecond: and the 12. of April at night of ſixth, a verie greate one, the blood for a greate vvhile running from her iuſt like a ſpiggot. The 15. of the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:50564:7"/> month, beeing ſaturday, she had a ſeaventh fit, farre mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re furious than any of the former, ſo as in leſſe than halfe an houres time she loſt 10. or 12. pound of blood; continuing alſo to bleed ſome vvhat for tvvo or three houres after; by the end vvhere-off the bleeding vvas ſtanched, she hauing been let blood in the arme, and manie good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies given her invvardlie, and applied outvvardlie, by me and the midvvife, vvith the joint advice of Doctor Sarraſin, an ancient and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb facs="tcp:50564:8"/> practioner. Yet she had another little shed the ſame day about tenne of the clock at night, a ſecond about the ſame houre the next morning, beeing ſunday; and a third at one the clock in the afternoon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and from that time the blood having ſtayed on her till the next day, monday the 17. of April, at ſeaven a clock at night, then again, notvvhitſtanding a greate manie of moſt excellent remedies, both outvvard and invvard, that had been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred to her everſince ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday
<pb facs="tcp:50564:8"/> at noon, (during vvhich time alſo she had not ſtirred out of her bed, and been plied vvith ſuch exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite nourishments, as are fitting and uſuall in the like caſes) the blood burſt dovvn in as greate an abundance as ever: vvhereby her veines, ſo much emptied alreadie, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing been utterlie exhauſted, it ſo abated her ſtrength, as caſting her from one fainting fit into another, vvithout anie thorough throvvs, for to bring-on labour, but onelie ſome vveak beginnings of it
<pb facs="tcp:50564:9"/> (to the contrary of vvhat the midvvife vvith us had hoped and expected) she ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver came to herſelfe again but gave up her ghoſte ſome three houres after the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this laſt fit, and about tenne of the clock at night having kept her ſences till vvithin a quarter of an houre afore she died, and her speech till vvithin leſſe than halfe an houre. And this laſt halfe houre she vvas vvonderfull calme and quiet, vvhere-as for the space of ſomevvhat more than halfe an houre
<pb facs="tcp:50564:9"/> before she had grievouſlie toſſed; her heart beeing loath to yeeld to the approches of death, becauſe not at all abated by anie ſicknes. For after every one of thoſe sheds, that she had had from the beginning, even after that late and grievous one on ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday, and after the ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent ones on ſunday; she did still recover herſelfe again vvithin a fevv houres, and vvould be very heartie, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting her meate vvith as good an appetite and digeſtion, as if she had ailed nothing.
<pb facs="tcp:50564:10"/> And having got a greate deale of good sleep the last night of her life, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvvixt ſunday and monday, she vvas ſo cheerfull and light ſome, not onelie in the morning, but all the day aſter, as if she had had no harme at all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and vvhere-as she had companie moſt part of the afternoon, she talked and vvas merry vvith them in the ſame manner, as any vvell bodie might have done. Inſomuch as Doctour Sarra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, vvho vvent not from her till a little before ſeaven
<pb facs="tcp:50564:10"/> of the clock at night (hauing been upvvards of an houre vvith her) vvent avvay full of moſt comfortable hopes, and aſſured me at parting, that there vvas nothing at all to be feared for her. For although she had not felt the child ſtirre at all ſince ſatur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day at noon, vve made the leſſe matter of that, becauſe that it having lyen still aſter ſeverall of the former fits in the ſame manner for the space of 24. houres, and longer, it vvas still come to itſelfe again: ſo as there vvas cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:50564:11"/> to hope for as much at the time. As for vvhat she ſaid and did in thoſe laſt houres of her life, and hovv she con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded it in relation to God and her ſoule, that vvill find a place in ſome part of the follovving Diſcourſe; the vvhich let us begin novv.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50564:11"/>
            <head>I.</head>
            <p>SHe feared God moſt trulie, and vvith a moſt upright heart, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring in all her actions, thoroughout the vvhole courſe of her life, to obſerve his holie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from all euill: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as she vvould not have co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted anie thing vvillinglie, that she vvas convinced to be contrary to his holy vvill, expreſſed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50564:12"/> in ſacred Vvrit, for an earthlie advantage vvhat ſo-ever; the preſerving of a good conſcience in a things, beeing the chief of her cares. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> she vvas vvonderfull reli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gious, ſo she vvas verie de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vout, never miſſing of performing her morning and evening prayers, of reading every day ſome portion of the holie Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, of dulie obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Lords day, of aſſiſting at Gods publick vvorship on the ſame,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50564:12"/> (vvithout ever abſenting herſelfe from it for anie ſmall hinderances) and of receiving frequentlie the holie communion; before vvhich she ever prepared herſelfe the eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning before verie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verentlie vvith fitting prayers and meditations, and vvith the like cloſed up that ſacred action, at her comming home from the ſame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in that exerciſe, as in other parts of her devotion, she hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped herſelfe much vvith
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50564:13"/> the formes ſet dovvn in the Practice of Pietie vvhere-off she vvas a great lover<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and she did l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kevviſe greatlie affect a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other books of devotion of meditations, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> morall inſtructions, pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vided that they vvere vvritten feelinglie, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidlie, and gravelie, for thoſe that vvere either dull, flat, and liveleſſe or ſtuffed vvith vvord rather than vvith matt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and puffed up vvith em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptie rhetorick, she did
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50564:13"/> not at all care for, as on all other ſubjects, ſo principallie on this.</p>
            <p>Having been bred a Proteſtant by her father, and by her mother (a meere ſaint of a vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) she vvas verie fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me in that profeſſion, and verie averſe from all the errours of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: for the confuting vvhereoff, and for the aſſerting of the truth, she vvould uphold a diſpute ſo handſomelie, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſuch ſolid and perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50564:14"/> arguments, as vvas not a little to be admi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red in her ſexe and age and having been ſeverall times tampered vvithall ſince her comming to Paris, by Prieſts and Friars, eſpecially of the Irish nation (vvho, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe of her belongins to that countrie by her father, pretended to be particularlie obliged, to have a care of converting her to their beleefe) she ever ſent them avvay ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peleſſe of effecting anie
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50564:14"/> thing upon her; ſo clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their mouths, upon vvhat point ſo ever they attaqued her, as she left them deſtitute of all ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid replies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and this she did vvith ſo much calme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as she never ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into the leaſt heate in any of thoſe diſputes.</p>
            <p>She vvas altogether ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to the conſtitution of the church of England, both for the governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and for the formes pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in the ſame; beeing verie much in love vvith
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50564:15"/> the common prayer, and greatlie admiring many particulars of it, as of the reſt of the Liturgie, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciallie the manner of ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miniſtring the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per, and of burying the dead<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet she vvas verie farre from being of their opinion, vvho looK o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the French Proteſtants as beeing of a different Religion; not thinking a fevv differences, in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantiall matters of government and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, a ſufficient ground
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50564:15"/> of making ſo great a diſtance betvvixt tvvo churches ſo unanimous in all eſſentials<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and this made her verie vvilling to goe to Charenton, and to find much comfort and ſatisfaction, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in aſſiſting at their ſermons and prayers, but in receiving the Lords ſupper vvith them; as she hath done verie oſten.</p>
            <p>She could in no vviſe indure anie expreſſions, that had anie thing of prophanenes in them,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50564:16"/> though othervviſe a grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te lover of vvittie and merrie ſayings: but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the contrary she ſingu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>larlie relished all diſcour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes of goodnes and pie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie, and vvould often fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on them herſelfe, vvhen that good occaſions vve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re offered, and vvhen she thought the compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nie vvould be delighted or edified by it: beeing verie farre from affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this, as in all other matters, and from deſiring to appeare reli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gious,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50564:16"/> rather than to bee ſo. She greatlie hated all ſingularities in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, either in matters of opinion, or of practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce; beeing a greate lover of conformitie. She had perfectlie thoſe tvvo qualities of David, of loving the godlie, and of hating the vvicked: and as she greatlie abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all levvd and profane perſons, ſo she did no ſooner perceive true goodnes and pietie in anie bodie, but she pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentlie
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50564:17"/> conceived a grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te friendship and affe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ction tovvards them.</p>
            <p>And the feare of God bore ſo abſolute a svvay in her ſoule, as it vvas the chief ground of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her other vertues and good qualities, for ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of them, as she vvas na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turallie inclined unto, o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther by the frame of her mind, or the temperature of her bodie, or both (vvhich vvere many, and of the chiefeſt) in then she vvas greatlie conſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50564:17"/> and ſtrengthened by this conſideration, that they vvere pleaſing to God Almightie, and commanded by him; oftentimes making that reflection<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and as for the others, vvhere-unto her nature vvas not ſo much diſpoſed of it ſelfe, or from vvhich it had ſome averſion, (as humilitie, long-ſuffering, contemt of the ſplendour and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of this vvorld) she did in them ſo ſtrive vvith herſelfe, out of a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50564:18"/> meere deſire or making herſelfe acceptable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God, and of performing his bleſſed command<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments; as she did not onelie novv and then by vvay of a temporary violence upon herſelfe performe ſome actions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thoſe vertues, contrary to her ovvne inclination onelie becauſe she knew them to be required <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God; but by her con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuall ſtudie and practi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> laboured to maKe the habituall to her, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:50564:18"/> a greate meaſure attained there-unto.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="text">
            <head>II.</head>
            <p>She vvas moſt exactlie iuſt, ſo as she vvould not have done anie bodie the leaſt vvrong in the vvorld, though it had been to benefit herſelfe never ſo much by it; and vvould rather have expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed herſelfe to anie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commoditie, than be vvanting in giuing every bodie their due to the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50564:19"/> full. vvhich alſo make her verie punctuall paying all kind of del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as ſoon as ever they vv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ovving, and called for never uſing nor en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring to make anie bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> call tvvice for vvhat v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be payed to them; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo farre from takin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pleaſure in keeping <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> her hands monies that vvere due, as she v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rather diſpleaſed vv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them, vvho vvere s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in comming to dem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them. And as she vvas
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50564:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſevere an obſerver of this vertue tovvards others, ſo she vvas verie remiſſe in exacting it from others to herſelfe; beeing of a vvonderfull yeelding na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and rather chuſing at anie time to goe from her right, than by ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding too preciſelie upon it, dravv-on anie oblo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie or ſtrife upon her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. It vvas from the dictates of Iuſtice, that she greatlie condemned all inſurrections vvhatſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ever, as beeing perſvva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50564:20"/> that abſolute obe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dience is due to the legiti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mate ſupreame Povvers and all forcible reſiſten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce againſt them forbid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den, though they acq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> themſelves never ſo ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the truſt committed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them by God and me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and commit never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> manie and ſo greate e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rours againſt equitie and reaſon, and againſt the fundamentall lavves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their countries. In vvhich perſvvaſion, mainly grounded on conſcie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50564:20"/> she did alſo greatlie ſtrengthen herſelfe by a prudentiall conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (frequentlie inſiſted upon by her in her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes) of the great evils, that manie times come to paſſe by reaſon of the like ſtirres; vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby the people, gulled by the cunning of a fevv factious and ambitious leaders (zealouſlie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the publick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, but reallie making that altogether ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient to the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50564:21"/> of their ov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unvvarrantable deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and deſſeins) doe co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monlie, inſteed of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding their conditio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fight themſelves int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much more grievous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verie, than that vvhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> before they ſuffered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> apprehended. It vv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from Iuſtice alſo, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> she vvas vvonderfull r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pective to all decay perſons, beeing verie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>refull to deferre as mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unto them, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them vvith all the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:50564:21"/> civilities, in their preſent lovv condition, that vve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re given or due unto them in the dayes of their beſt fortune<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and this she obſerved not onelie tovvards others of that kind, vvith vvhom she had not anie particular commerce, but even unto them, vvho in ſome ſort depended on her, and vvho often taſted of the fruites of her bountie: she thinKing it verie hard and unreaſonable, that vvhat vvas trulie due to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50564:22"/> a bodie for ſome in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> rent qualitie, should <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> denied them becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their misfortune; gri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vous enough to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> borne, vvithout a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch aggravation.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="text">
            <head>III.</head>
            <p>As she deteſted all i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> juſtice to all kind of pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons, ſo eſpeciallie th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvhich vvas exerciſe againſt infirme ones vvanting meanes an friends for to helpe an
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50564:22"/> right themſelves; of vvhoſe condition she vvas vvonderfull ſenſible, and vvonderfull prone to comfort and releeve them to the beſt of her povver; as likevviſe all other perſons diſtreſſed vvith anie calamities, unto vvhom she vvas ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedinglie tenderhearted and compaſſionate. This made her verie charitable and openhanded to all ſuch, as farre as her ovvn abilities vvould any vvayes give her leave: the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50564:23"/> inlarging vvhere-off sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deſired for nothing el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo much, as that there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> she might be inabled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> doe the more good unt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the needie; vvhereas elſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſetting that conſider<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion apart, she h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> brought herſelfe to an a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolute contentednes vvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that mediocrity of fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tune, vvhich the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvas pleaſed to affo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us. And as her com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paſſionate nature ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her to have a verie de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fellovv-feeling of oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:50564:23"/> folkes vvant and pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and to be verie free in imparting her ovvne unto them, vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvithall to releeve their neceſſities; ſo she had a verie livelie ſence of all their other ſufferings, and conſequentlie did excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinglie deteſt all kind of crueltie. For her hearte vvas ſo vvonderfull ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as her compaſſion extended itſelfe not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie unto all chriſtians, and unto all mankind, euen unto ſuch vvho by their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50564:24"/> ovvn miſdoings h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> brought upon themſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ves the evill they ſuffer (except onelie thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvho beeing guiltie ſome verie hainous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes, vvere unto her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> objects of meere horro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> she obdurating her h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againſt them out of me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtrength of iudgeme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> but it reached alſo to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> verie dumb and unr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonable creatures: u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvhom she could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> onelie not find in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> heart to doe anie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:50564:24"/> leaſt harme, or indure others to doe it; but if caſuallie anie hurt vvas befalne them, it vvould verie much trouble her, and she vvould not omit anie indeavours for to helpe them out of their paines. and I have ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall times obſerved vvith vvonderment, hovv her mind vvould be diſquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if but a bird, or anie other domeſtick creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, had anie harme come to them, and hovv ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlie diligent she vvould
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50564:25"/> be in ſeeking to eaſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to releeve them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="text">
            <head>IV.</head>
            <p>As her charitie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> verie greate in the af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaid particulars, ſo it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> no leſſe in maKing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> beſt of other fol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> actions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and inſteed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> beeing the firſt in de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting them, or putt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g an evill conſtruct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n upon them; she vvo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d ever taKe their part, v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o vvere ſo dealt vvith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:50564:25"/> beeing ſo farre from ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king anie delight in back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting, and in detracting from others (a vice ſo common novv adayes amongſt all kind of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as in moſt compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, eſpeciallie of vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, it is the principall ſubject of peoples diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes) as she vvould ever reſiſt them that did ſo: and that not onelie in the behalfe of perſons, to vvhom she had anie relation, or obligation, but even to meere ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50564:26"/> yea and to perſons vvho had dealt unKindli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvith her, or anie vvay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> offended her; and to ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alſo many times, vvh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by their ovvne depor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments had given th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvorld iuſt cauſe of ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pecting the vvorſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them. It is true, that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch deportments vve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> condemned by her vvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much ſeveritie; her ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie being no vvay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> blind, nor at all ove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> clouding her iudgeme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and her inbred hatred
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50564:26"/> vice and all vicious actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. But she could not give her aſſent to thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences, vvhich uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie are dravvne from them, except the matter vvere vvonderfull evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> neither did a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon report, or generall rumour, ſvvay her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe much in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular: she perſvvading herſelfe, and that not vvithout good ground, that many have ſuffered injuſtlie in their reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vvithout being
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50564:27"/> reallie guiltie of the crimes or follies, vvhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvith common fame h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> branded them. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this her charitie vv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> common to all ſorts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> perſons, ſo she did i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> peculiar manner app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it to them of the ſupr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> me degrees: in vvh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nevertheleſſe, as in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> others, she did verie mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> condemne not onelie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch carriage, as had a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thing of indiſcretion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of looſnes in it, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thereby gave ſome p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50564:27"/> grounds of ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting and ſpeaking the vvorſt of them; but even thoſe actions, vvhich beeing in themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and of an indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent nature, vvere knovvne to themſelves to be looked-on vvith ſcandall, and to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance vvhere-off no neceſſitie at all obliged them: vvhich to have been the caſe, ſome yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſince, of ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of greateſt eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, in this and other
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50564:28"/> neighbouring countri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is obvious to every ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> knovvledge, vvho is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a meere ſtranger to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> paſſages of the times.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="text">
            <head>V.</head>
            <p>Her charitie vvas lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviſe ſingular in fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving all manner <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vvrongs and offence<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> though never ſo groſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or ſo malicious; and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not onelie upon indea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vours of reconciliation but before anie ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50564:28"/> given. And ſo farre she vvas from harbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring anie ſpleene, or anie thoughts of revenge, tovvards them that had done her anie iniurie; as she did not onelie par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don them from all her ſoule, and heartilie prayed God to doe the ſame; but vvas verie vvilling and readie, to doe them anie good offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, not onelie in that nature, of vvhich vvee have ſpoKen in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going article, but on
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50564:29"/> all other occaſions, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preſented themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to her. And her charit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvas ſo compleate in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> particular, and accomp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nied vvith ſo much gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>roſitie, as nothing cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> have rejoiced her mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> than to have it in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> povver, to doe ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> greate courteſie un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them, vvho had deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ved the the quite contrary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> her; and she vvould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſure to doe it, if the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>portunitie offered itſelf</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="text">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:50564:29"/>
            <head>VI.</head>
            <p>She vvas vvonderfull liberall of her nature, vvhich qualitie as it vvell helped-on her charitie, in beeing communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve of releefe to the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ſo it made her come-off verie handſomelie, according to her ovvne condition, vvith all other matters of expence; lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving much rather not to doe at all ſuch things, as might convenientlie be
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50564:30"/> omitted, than not to doe them compleatlie. yet vvas she verie farre from beeing a prodigall: and as her ovvne inclination did altogether exemt her from niggardlynes, and from all things that might in anie vviſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that vvay, ſo her judgement gave a ſvveet mixture of frugalitie to her liberalitie, making her exactlie vvarie of ſpending anie thing on vanitie, or pleaſures: as on the other ſide she
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:50564:30"/> vvould alvvayes much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther have choſen to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mmodeate herſelfe, than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot to fulfill the utmoſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f vvhat decencie, yea <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd generoſitie too, did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>quire. And as in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atter of apparell, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iture, and attendaunce, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e could have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent to goe to the moſt expenſive magnificence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat anie vvayes might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ute vvith her qualitie; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> grace and vviſdome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade her over-rule vvhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver there vvas too much
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50564:31"/> of this in her naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, and acquieſce vvith a full contentment of mind in a comelie mediocritie; yea and to reſt ſatisfied vvith leſſe too, vvhen that either the publick calamities, or ſome of our ovvn pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate emergencies, did ſo require it. And in this, as in other particulars, her mind vvas of that svveet and happie tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, as she ever kept her deſires vvithin thoſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, that reaſon and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:50564:31"/> goodnes did preſcribe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto her; and vvhen she <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad attained to vvhat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vith their approbation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he had propounded unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſelfe, she reſted there, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vith an abſolute conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ednes; no vvayes like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto moſt perſons, vvho <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lilating their lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to vvhat is remote, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> little or no taſte in vvhat they doe injoy for the preſent, though for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merlie the utmoſt of their vvishes, aſpiring ſtill after nevv inlargements.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="text">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:50564:32"/>
            <head>VII.</head>
            <p>She loved all kind of ſummerfruit exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, as moſt young fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, eſpeciallie of that ſexe, uſe to doe: and she could never frame her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to an abſolute and conſtant forbearance of it, although her he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs did ſeeme ſo to requi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e it, and that the plenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full uſe of the ſame did from time to time ſubject her to ſeverall little acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:50564:32"/> and infirmities. But for all other things, never man or vvoman leſſe loved their bellies, than she did; she taKing-up moſt contentedlie at anie time vvith moſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie food, ſo it vvere but good and vvholſome; and neither longing for more exquiſite dishes, vvhen she had them not; nor taking anie ſingular delight in them, vvhen that at anie time for my ſaKe, or for the reception of ſome friend, she had
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:50564:33"/> provided anie; or that abroad, either at a friends houſe, or in the countrie upon a iournie of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, she met vvith anie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and she vvould let the vvhole yeare paſſe, vvit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout ſo much as once cooking anie thing for herſelfe, or hauing anie particular dish prepared for her. And yet she vvas not ſo indifferent, nor her mouth ſo out of taſt, but that she did perfectlie vvell relish the finer and delicater meates
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:50564:33"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bove the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ones, and in her ovvne inclinations like ſeverall kinds of food be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but to buy that little pleaſure, vvhich she took in them, at the expence of anie great coſt or trouble, that she could never find in her heart to doe. As for vvine, or anie ſtrong drinks vvhatſo ever, she never knevv vvhat it vvas to love them: and vvhen she took anie (as she did vvonderfull ſeldome, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:50564:34"/> in verie ſmall quantities) it vvas meerlie in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a medecin. And as to confitures, and all kind of ſvveet-meates, she cared not at all for them, nor could indure anie more than to taſte of them, and ſcarce that neither, even vvhen they coſt her nothing.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="text">
            <head>VIII.</head>
            <p>Her chaſtitie vvas alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether extraordinarie; and as vvith a ſingular
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50564:34"/> care she ever kept her reputation moſt abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telie unſpotted, never having committed anie action, that might have afforded anie the leaſt ground or colour of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie to the moſt mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious slaunderers: ſo she never knevv, vvhat it vvas to have anie the leaſt inclination or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation of ſinning that vvay. And indeed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the prevalencie of grace and goodnes in her, the verie temper of her
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:50564:35"/> bodie made het ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute a ſtranger to all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full luſts, as she never knevv vvhat it vvas to take anie the leaſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in our verie conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall imbraces, or in all that time, that vvee vvere married together (beeing upvvards of eight yeares) ſo much as once to yeeld unto the performance of the ſame, vvithout ſome reluctancie, nor other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviſe than in maKing ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me effort upon herſelfe for the paying of a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:50564:35"/> bounden dutie. And this her naturall coldnes as it made her verie apt to judge the beſt of other vvomen, vvhoſe publick misbehaviour did not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penlie ſpeake them guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and to misbeleeve all or moſt part of vvhat vvas ſaid of their contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſpoſition (as not able to conceive that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily in others, ſo much the contrary vvhere-off she found in herſelfe) ſo it gave her cauſe oftentimes to ſay, vvhen
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:50564:36"/> in our private diſcourſes vvee vvould freelie ſpeak our minds one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that chaſtitie vvas no vertue at all in her, and that she did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve anie commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for poſſeſſing it; no more than a man, vvho naturallie careth not for vvine, doth merit ani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prayſes for beeing no drunkard. And as she vvas chaſt in this high degree, ſo she vvas no leſſe modeſt and shame faſt; vvhich qualitie, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:50564:36"/> vvell as the dictates of grace, made her that she <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould not indure anie vvanton and laſcivious expreſſions, not onelie not foule and broad ones, but even ſuch as but darklie or glauncinglie tended that vvay: at the vvhich, if it vvere her fortune to be in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie vvhere anie ſuch thing vvas ſpoken, she vvould blush as much, and be as much diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as could be expected of a little maiden of the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:50564:37"/> beſt nature and educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And indeed at the very firſt aſpect one might readily read this qualitie in her face, her ordinary countenance holding forth a moſt ſvveet and a moſt perfect modeſtie.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="text">
            <head>IX.</head>
            <p>But the aforeſaid coldnes of her temper did no vvayes hinder her of beeing moſt fervent in her affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tovvards me
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:50564:37"/> nor of bearing me ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere and ſo intire a love, as I beleeve to be equalled but by fevv vvives: and ſure I am, it can be excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by none. This made her to deſire to have ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie much of my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie, never beeing better plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, than vvhen she had me neere her; to be vvon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull ſollicitous in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing me all manner of contentment, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting all cauſes of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure; to comply vvith my inclinations, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:50564:38"/> applaud my reſolutions, except she ſavv or appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended ſome great cauſe to the contrary (vvhich then verie ſvveetlie and prudentlie she vvould lay open to me) and indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to the utmoſt of her povver to further and effect them; and to be ſo vvonderfull tender of me, that if anie the leaſt thing ailed me, and if but my finger aked, she vvas all out of order, and could not quiet her ſelfe, till she knevv <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:50564:38"/> vvas better vvith me. And not onelie at other times it vvas ſo vvith her, but even vvhen she vvas no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vvell herſelfe, and vvhen she vvas troubled vvith anie paine or acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent vvhat-ever; the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vvhere-off could not in the leaſt vviſe hinder that her tendernes over me: vvhich made me ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vvarie at all times hovv I did complaine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her of anie slight matter; for feare of diſquieting her more
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:50564:39"/> than the matter vvas vvorth. And in that ſicknes, vvherevvith it pleaſed God to viſit me in the beginning of the yeare 1646. (the onelie that I had, ſince vvee vvere married together) and vvhich, by reaſon of a relapſe, Kept m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> betvvixt tvvo ana thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vveeks in my bed, sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvas ſo aſſiduous abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> me, tooke ſo much pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vvith me, (although ſhe vvas then ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> months gone vvith chil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:50564:39"/> and needed not to have done anie thing herſelfe, vvee having more ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants than one about us) and did ſo lay my caſe to heart, as none but a moſt excellent vvife vvould have done the ſame. And vvithall she uſed ſo much diſcretion and circumſpection, that as oft as her grief, out of the apprehenſion of my danger, came to that height, that she could no longer keep it in, but that she muſt needs
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:50564:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> vent it in teares and ſobs (vvhich befell her verie often) she vvould be ſure to retire to a corner, vvhere I should neither ſee nor heare her, for feare of aggravating my indiſpoſition by her grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="text">
            <head>X.</head>
            <p>And as to me, ſo t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her children, her affectio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvas vvonderfull great<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and tender, vvhich mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her take her principal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> delight in them, vvhile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:50564:40"/> she injoyed them, and heavilie to mourne after them, vvhen the Lord took them from us; as he did the ſecond, beeing a boy, on the 15. of May 1649. beeing then ſeaven months old: and the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, vvhich vvas a girle, on the ſecond of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 1647. she then beeing come to the age of three yeares compleatlie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the loſſe of this child did not onelie afflict her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamlie for the preſent, (as that of the boy did
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:50564:41"/> too) but for a greate vvhile, and many months after: during all vvhich time she shed abundance of teares for her. Indeed the girle vvas a moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velie one, beeing of moſt exquiſite features, and of a moſt pure complexion: and therebeſides (vvhich vvas much more to be valued, and accordinglie valued by the mother) there appeared in her, as much as could appeare in that tender age, not onelie a vvonderfull
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:50564:41"/> good vvit, but all the ſignes of a ſvveet diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of mind, and of a good and vertuous natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re; vvhereby she had got the love of all that knevv her: ſo as it vvas no vvonder, if the Mothers heart vvas extreamlie ſet upon her. And the Lord having given a good sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of the ſame advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, both of bodie and of mind, to our laſt girle too; the mothers affection, ever guided as much by iudgement as
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:50564:42"/> by inſtinct, vvas not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie as exceſſive to her, as it had been to the other, but she took yet greater joy and contentment in her, than she had done in the former: Becauſe that the indovvments of the mind, the chief ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the Mothers affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, shevved forth themſelves more mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtlie and fullie in her than they had done i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our eldeſt girle, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as she vvas com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſome greater ripen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:50564:42"/> of age, than the other had lived unto; beeing foure yeares and a halfe old, vvhen the Mother dyed. And my Love fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding every day more and more, that beſides the ſvveetnes of her nature, free from all vicious and perverſe inclinations (ſome or other vvhere-off doe appeare in moſt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren) a greate flexibilitie tovvards all good inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary avvfulnes of all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, ſo as a vvord
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:50564:43"/> and a threate vvould do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more vvith her, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> blovves vvith others; sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvas alſo verie capable and vvithall not oneli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvilling, but greatlie de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſirous of learning, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſequentlie moſt ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceptible of all good edu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cation: she took ſo grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a felicitie in her, that ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> she had but the chil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neere her, she nev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> found the miſſe of ani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other companie; vvhic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> othervviſe, her natu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> beeing verie ſociable
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:50564:43"/> she loved vvonderfull vvell. And as before, ſo much more during the time that she altogether Kept her chamber (as she did for the ſpace of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven vveeks, ever ſince that firſt accident on the firſt of March) she ſpent the greateſt part of her time vvith her; partlie in teaching her to pray, and making her repeate often the Lords prayer, and ſeverall other good prayers, as likevviſe the Creed, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements;
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:50564:44"/> partlie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> catechiſing her about th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> principall points of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, making her every day repea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvhat she had learned b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, vvith ſome ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> additions ſtill from tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> time; partlie in teachin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her the beginnings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reading, vvhich she di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvith ſo much ſucces, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in a fevv vveeks the chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> had perfectlie learned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> her letters, and the ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling of all ſingle ſyllabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vvith good progre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:50564:44"/> tovvards the ſpelling of the more compounded ones, and of ſome vvhole vvords; and laſtlie in anſvvering the childs que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions (moſt of vvhich vvere vvonderfull prettie and vvittie) and in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>King all occaſions, both by them, and othervviſe too, of begetting and confirming in her the knovvledge and love of vertue, pietie, and civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. And finding all the paines, vvhich she took vvith the child,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:50564:45"/> vvonderfull effectuall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that did ſo inflame h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> affection tovvards h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> more and more, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> adde ſo much to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> greate pleaſure and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pynes, vvhich she shape<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unto herſelfe in havin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her neere her, as s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vvould needs dreſſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> child every morning he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe, and ſpend an hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or tvvo about it, inſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of letting one of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> maids doe it, as they uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to doe, vvhen the chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vvas younger yet: a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:50564:45"/> she vvould never have loſt her out of her ſight, if she vvould have looked onelie to her ovvn con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment. But her judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment overruling her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination in this, as in other particulars, she vvould every day for a greate vvhile deprive her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of her, not onelie vvhen she had companie, but even at other times too; for feare of making the child mopish, and to give her time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create herſelfe vvith play,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:50564:46"/> the moderate uſe vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>off she knevv to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutelie neceſſary for children. But although her love and her indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence tovvards her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren vvas thus exceſſive, yet it vvas no vvayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fond one, but tempered vvith ſo much ſeveritie as she vvould never vvin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at anie of their faults nor let them goe unco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rected, vvhen-ever the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had done ſome thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> amiſſe; as no children<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> though of never ſo goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:50564:46"/> a nature, are alvvayes exempt from commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſome childish fault, or other.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="text">
            <head>XI.</head>
            <p>Her love and affection, vvhich vvas thus fervent to her husband and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, vvas nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe to her other rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, eſpeciallie to her parents and tvvo bto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but as intire and as greate, as could be expected of a perſon of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:50564:47"/> ſo much grace and good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes. This made he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lay verie much to hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the death of her eldeſt brother, VVilliam Dun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gan, vvho hauing had the command, for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpace of a yeare and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> halfe, of a companie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> tvvo hundred fire-loc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the kings ſervice, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the late vvarres of Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land, and shevved mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gallantrie and coura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> on all occaſions, vv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> one of the princip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> actours in the taking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:50564:47"/> Leiceſter, a fevv dayes before the battle of Nazeby; vvhere having led on the ſouldiours the third time to the aſſault, after that they had been tvvice beaten-off, he vvas at his verie entring into the tovvn shot tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the bodie vvith a musket-bullet, of vvhich he died vvithin a fevv houres after; beeing ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie much lamented by all them that knevv him, eſpeciallie by his Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, Prince Rupert, vvho
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:50564:48"/> in a particular manne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> affected him for his va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lour, diligence, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie. This loſſe, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> brother in the flovver o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his youth (for he vva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not above 23. yeares old vvhen he dyed) vvhom she had ever loved moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tenderlie, and vvhom s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> eſteemed highlie for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> brave qualities; havin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been redoubled vvit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the loſſe of her mothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one of the beſt mothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that ever vvas; vvh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had taken her ſons dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:50564:48"/> ſo much to heart, as it put her into a conſomtion, vvhereof she died vvithin a fevv months after: she vvas readie to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvhelmed vvith grief, if the confort, vvhich she took in me and her child, had not ſuſtained her, till other and ſublimer conſiderations, of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to Gods vvill, and taking all patienlie at his hands, could take place in her diſtreſſed mind. But as it had afflicted her verie much,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:50564:49"/> that the deſolate eſtate of Ireland, and the exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of my affaires, had neceſſitated me to bring her avvay from Dublin in the beginning of the yeare 1644. and thereby to ſeparate her at a greate diſtance, as from the reſt of her friends and kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred (vvho all vvere excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſorrie to part vvith her) ſo from her deare Parents, vvhere-unto ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe she ſubmitted vvillinglie, and vvithout repining, as knovving
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:50564:49"/> that my reſolution to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ounded on unanſvvere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le reaſons: ſo she did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ceſſivelie long, after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e death of her brother <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d mother, more yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>an ever before, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rne into Ireland, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be a comfort to her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood father in that ſad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nelyneſſe, vvhere-unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat grievous double <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſſe had reduced him. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or she loved him as much, as ever child lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a father, not onelie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut of a naturall inſtinct,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:50564:50"/> as he vvas her father, but upon the conſideration, that he had ever been a moſt loving and moſt indulgent father to her; and that as he had put her into the vvorld, ſo he had had a ſingular care, together vvith the mother (a vvoman of a moſt ſanctified mind and converſation) to bring her up in the feare of God, and in the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: and vvithall had never ſpared anie paines or coſts on her, for to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:50564:50"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve her the verie beſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeding, that the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e could afford, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave her thoroughlie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ructed in all thoſe qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ties, that are anie vvayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>quiſite for the making-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p of a moſt compleate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>entlevvoman, viz per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ect skill in all kind of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eedlevvork, the french <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anguage, dauncing, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ick; the lute, and other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſtruments. And her deſire, of returning to her father on the ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rounds, beeing ſo full
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:50564:51"/> of pietie and reaſon, I vvould long ſince have accomplished it, if the publicK condition of Ireland, and the conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency of mine ovvne affaires, vvould in anie vviſe have given vvay to it. VVhich she per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectlie vvell knovving, and that it vvas not vvant of good vvill, that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered me from giving her ſatisfaction in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; she ſtrove to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent herſelfe the beſt she could, and to conſole her
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:50564:51"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nging vvith theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, that the ſame lets, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vhich hindered us for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he preſent from retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing to Dublin, vvould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot laſt alvvayes; but that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he times mending, she vvould yet goe back to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reland, and there be a ſtay and comfort to her good father all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of his dayes. But it hath pleaſed God to diſpoſe othervviſe of it, and in her to deprive him, as vvell as me, of the chiefeſt ioy that vvee
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:50564:52"/> had in this vvorld.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="text">
            <head>XII.</head>
            <p>As she eſteemed it her greateſt happines, that God had done her the grace to call her to the knovvledge of his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving truth, and to the aſſured hopes of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting bliſſe, by making her a chriſtian, of the Reformed Religion, and that reallie and ſincerely, not in outvvard profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion onely; for vvhich
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:50564:52"/> she gave dailie moſt hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thanks unto his Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Majeſtie: ſo she ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted it one of her greateſt temporall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, to be of a good extraction. And that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed vvas as good, as anie could be under the degree of nobilitie: the Dungans (of vvhich houſe her father, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Dungan, Iuſtice of the Court of Common Pleas at Dublin, is a younger brother) beeing of the auncienteſt and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:50564:53"/> beſt gentrie of Ireland, and allied not onelie vvith moſt of the prime gentrie of the Pale, as the Talbots, the Roche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, the Ashpooles, the VVogans, etc. but even vvith ſeverall Noble hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. And as for her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall line, that vvas no vvayes inferiour to the other: the Palmers of Nottinghamshire (of vvhich her mother, Grace Palmer, vvas borne) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though but a younger braunch of the Palmers
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:50564:53"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Lemingthon, in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ountie of Gloceſter, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving alvvayes ſubſiſted verie honourablie, and been reckoned among the beſt houſes of that countrie. And she ſet ſo high a value upon this qualitie, that if it had been poſſible for her to forgoe vvhat nature and her birth had given her, she vvould not have accepted of the vvealth and ſplendour of a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, on condition of not beeing borne a
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:50564:54"/> gentlevvoman. Yet for all this no bodie did or could more, than she, deſpiſe a gentleman or gentlevvoman, vvhoſe qualities and actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vvere not correſpondent to their extraction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and not onelie vice and vvicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes made her looſe all eſteeme in their behalfe (as to the contrarie she greatlie valued even the meaneſt perſons, in vvhom she perceived true goodnes and vertue) but alſo ill-bred carria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:50564:54"/> and all incivilitie and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udenes: uſing to ſay oftentimes, that in vaine they ſtood upon their gentrie, though deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of never ſo good houſes, vvhoſe behaviour and manners vvere groſſe and plebejan; and beeing herſelfe not onelie verie civill, after the exacteſt and compleateſt manner, but vvonderfull gentill in all her actions, by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as vvell as by edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and ſo vvithout all affectation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and she
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:50564:55"/> vvould come-off vvo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hand-ſomelie vvith all Kind of complements, having naturallie a greate veine and copiouſnes that vvay, both in vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of letters, and in diſcourſing; and yet beeing verie judicious in not making uſe of them but verie ſeaſonablie, and as vvas moſt fitting and requiſite according to the diverſitie of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall occaſions.</p>
            <p>VVithall she vvas a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te hater of all proud and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:50564:55"/> haughtie deportments: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing herſelfe ſo cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous and affable, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nelie to her equals, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lſo to her inferiours, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe of the verie meaneſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt not excepted, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad anie occaſion to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome at her, as she vvon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir hearts extreamlie. vvherefore alſo not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie her friends, but alſo all thoſe mechanick and miniſteriall perſons, vvho either uſed to come con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantlie to the houſe, and to be imployed by her,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:50564:56"/> or had at anie time had anie dealing at all vvith her, vvere extreamlie grieved at her deceaſe; there beeing verie fevv of that vvhole number, vvho did not vvitneſſe their ſorrovv for it vvith abundance of teares. And yet her carriage tovvards this Kind of people vvas ever verie free from all meanenes, she behaving herſelfe vvith an exact mediocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie betvvixt ſcornefull contemt and an over-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>opular
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:50564:56"/> familiaritie.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="text">
            <head>XIII.</head>
            <p>Beeing of a verie ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iable nature, she loved good companie verie much, and to ſpend ſome houres at convenient ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes in making or recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving viſits. And as she vvas fit for all kind of diſcourſes, and could not onelie be content, but took greate delight in entering and dvvelling on ſerious matters, vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:50564:57"/> of ſtate-affaires and the paſſages of the times, or of things belonging to Moralitie or Divinitie, vvhen that the grauitie of the companie, or other good occaſions made them neceſſary or ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable; she acquitting herſelfe verie vviſelie and ſolidlie of them, to the greate ſatisfaction of them that she diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vvithall: ſo natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rallie she vvas verie much taken vvith all kind of vvittie converſation, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:50564:57"/> herſelfe a verie rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die vvit, and a verie quick apprehenſion; by reaſon vvhere-off alſo she vvas ever verie apt to learne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and as she attained verie ſoon, beeing yet a child, to all thoſe things, that she vvas inſtructed in, even to admiration; ſo ſince our comming to Paris she perfected her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the french ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue in much leſſe time, than vvhat is uſuall unto moſt others. And for the ſame reaſon she bore
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:50564:58"/> alſo a greate love to all other productions of vvit, eſpeciallie to good verſes and poemes, and to elegant vvell contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Romants, or fained hiſtories, ſuch as Sidneys Arcadia, Aſtrea, Ariana, the Illuſtrious Bashavv, and above all thoſe tvvo late ones of Mons<hi rend="sup">r</hi> de Calleprenette, ſo much admired univerſallie, Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandra and Cleopatra; on the reading of vvhich choice Romants she did vvith much contentment
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:50564:58"/> beſtovv ſome part of her time novv and then: beeing vvonderfullie pleaſed, as vvith the beautie of their language and conceptions, ſo vvith the characters off all kind of heroicall vertues, vvhich therein are held forth moſt livelie in the perſons of both ſexes. But as greate a lover as she vvas of vvit, and of all the productions of it; the leaſt mixture of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanenes, obſcenenes, or laſciviouſnes, did ſo
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:50564:59"/> ſovvre them unto her, as she did not onelie looſe all pleaſure in them, vvhen ſo tainted, but she did perfectlie loath and deteſt them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="text">
            <head>XIV.</head>
            <p>She vvas alſo vvonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſcreet in her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and ever uſed a ſingular care and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection in not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving anie offence to anie bodie; avoiding not onelie all kind of taunts
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:50564:59"/> reproaches, and bitter ieſts and ſcoffes (the vvhich she alſo verie much condemned in others, vvho uſed them before her) but all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, even vvhere the argument maintained vvas no vvayes to her mind; except the matter vvas of that importaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, as she thought her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe bound to expreſſe her diſliKe or contrary judgement abour it; vvhich ſo itſelfe she
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:50564:60"/> vvould doe vvith much vvarynes and mildnes. And although that in them, vvith vvhom she converſed, she could in no vviſe avvay vvith va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and bragging, nor vvith lying or unlikelie tales, thoſe tvvo faults beeing point blanck con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to her ovvn diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and practiſe; as not neither vvith ſtupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie and dulnes, a defect ſo extreamlie remote from her nature: yet out of meere ſtrength of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:50564:60" rendition="simple:additions"/> judgement (vvherevvith God had indovved her in a greate meaſure, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though for the moſt part vvit and judgement doe not uſe to goe together) she had brought herſelfe to ſo abſolute a habit of patientlie induring thoſe and other impertine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cies, as she vvould not in the leaſt manner expreſſe her diſlike there-off unto them, that she found guiltie of the ſame, nor in anie vviſe take notice there-off, by her vvords
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:50564:61"/> or actions. And as in theſe, ſo in all other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, she ſtudied to render herſelfe altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther complaiſant, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying, unto them, vvith vvhom she did converſe, though manie times greatlie againſt her ovvne liking: never breaking the rule, vvhich here-in she had preſcribed unto herſelfe, but vvhere by decencie, honour, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſcience, she found herſelfe indiſpenſeabli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> obliged to the contrary</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="text">
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:50564:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>XV.</head>
            <p>She that vvas thus cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect in giving no offence by her vvords and converſation, may eaſilie be conceived to have been verie farre from beeing offenſive in her actions. And ſo she vvas indeed, having a perpetuall vvatch over herſelfe, not to doe anie thing, vvhere at anie bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die might juſtlie be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: but to the contrary
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:50564:62"/> omitting no occaſions of doing every bodie all the good offices, that anie vvayes lay in her povver, and taKing a ſingular pleaſure in obliging others. And this she did vvith ſo much generoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that vvhere-as she never loſt the memorie of anie good turnes, that had been done her by others, but vvould uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all poſſible meanes for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> requite them, and on all occaſions expreſſe he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſence and thankfull
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:50564:62"/> acknovvledgement of the ſame; ſo on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary she never thought much of the good she had done to others, and could not indure to ſpeake of it, or to have it ſpoKe off, anie kind of vvay, much leſſe by vvay of upbraiding; even not in caſe of unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, and vvhere the parties obliged vvere al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unmindfull of the benefits received, or furthermore ſo farre for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate themſelves, as to
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:50564:63"/> requite good vvith evill.</p>
            <p>Neither could anie ſuch provocation at anie time prevaile vvith her, for to diſcover other folkes ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crets, not onelie ſuch as had been confided to her by the parties them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but even thoſe that othervviſe and acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentallie vvere come to her knovvledge. And as she vvas thus exact and conſcientious in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing of ſecrets; ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver anie bodie gave leſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvay to that curioſitie
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:50564:63"/> ſo ordinarie in the vvorld, of inquiring into the condition and affaires of other people: beeing ſo farre from ſeeking to pry into them, as she vvould not give anie the leaſt incouragement unto ſuch, vvho upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and of their ovvn accord, did happen at anie time to make anie ſuch thing knovvne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="text">
            <head>XVI.</head>
            <p>VVhat I have ſaid of
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:50564:64"/> her greate complying in converſation, even to the induring patientlie of the faults, defects, and impertinencies of others, is the more to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, becauſe that natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallie, and by the temper of her bodie, she vvas much inclined to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerick, and to be vexed at anie thing, great or ſmall, that vvas not to her mind. But never anie bodie of that conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did more earneſtli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and more effectuallie
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:50564:64"/> ſtrive to overcome it: vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby as she had made a greate progres tovvards the acquiring of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary habit, inſomuch as manie times she vvould put-up not onelie ſmall matters, but even greate and ſenſible offences, vvithout beeing much mooved at them, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ordinarilie, for to avoid all occaſion of putting herſelfe into anie heate, diſſemble the faults and miſdoings of her ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and of others, if
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:50564:65"/> she vvas not abſolutelie neceſſitated to take noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of them: ſo at the vvorſt, and even vvhen that the ſuddainnes of ſome un-expected pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation or indignitie vvrought on her naturall diſpoſition, and ſtirred her up to anger; the vvorſt effects of it vvere no other, than ſome sharp expreſſions. For she ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knevv vvhat it vvas to uſe injuries, or oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious language, much leſſe anie further effects
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:50564:65"/> of choller, no not to her ovvn ſervants, though never ſo much mooved. And as her anger vvas thus gentle, ſo it vvas vvonderfull short, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing avvay in a moment; eſpeciallie if thoſe, vvith vvhom she vvas offended, did not by their obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and offenſive replies miniſter anie nevv fevvell to it. And no ſooner vvas she come to herſelfe, but she vvould be the firſt in condemning, her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, if she found that
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:50564:66"/> she had at all overshot herſelfe, and ſpoke anie thing more harshlie or tartlie, than she thought she ought to have done.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="text">
            <head>XVII.</head>
            <p>She vvas a greate lover of Peace: and as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of preſerving it to herſelfe, made her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame vvary of offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding others in the leaſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, either by vvord o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deed, vvhich might mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter anie cauſe or pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>text
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:50564:66"/> unto them of falling-out vvith her; and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble anie ſuch offence given to herſelfe by others, if the nature of it, or the manner of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting it, dit not make it altogether incapable of beeing diſſembled: ſo she vvas ever verie ſtudious, of preſerving it alſo among others. For to tell tales, vvhereby to make people have an evill opinion one of another, and to ſet them by the eares together, vvas a
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:50564:67"/> thing utterlie unknovvne to her, as to her ovvne practice, and extreamlie deteſted by her in them that vvere guiltie of it. And if it fell out ſo, as ſome times it did, that tvvo perſons of her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, beeing either openlie fallen-out amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g themſelves, or bearing ſome ſecret grudge on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to another, told he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> things to the prejudic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of their adverſaries: sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvould be ſo farre from giving the parties intere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſted
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:50564:67"/> anie full or cleere knovvledge of the things that had been ſo vvhiſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto her, or making anie direct relation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>off to them, as she vvould not ſo much as give them the leaſt hint of anie ſuch matter. And vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as her good mother had ever obſerved, not to ſuffer her children to come and tell her her ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the ſervants, even vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that reallie they had done ſomething amiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe; leaſt they should get a
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:50564:68"/> habit, if countenanced there-in, of tale-telling ſo my deare Love vvas re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, and had begun to obſerve the ſame rul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tovvards our children that vveaning them fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their infancie of that vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo hatefull to her, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> beeing maKe-bates, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſovvers of diſcord and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>viſion; she might forr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them to the contrary v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue, conſonant to l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ovvn conſtant practi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of rather excuſing ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> folkes actions, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:50564:68"/> ever the beſt of the ſame, vvhereby to preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve peace and quietnes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="text">
            <head>XVIII.</head>
            <p>God having indovved her vvith a verie large share of handſomnes, and given her vvith a middlemoſt ſtature (ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvhat inclining to the leſſe, but vvonderfull neatlie timbred, vvith a moſt exact shape and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of all her limbs) a verie lovelie face, made-up
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:50564:69"/> of ſingular good fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures, an excellent eye, moſt fine skinne, and verie pure complexion she vvas verie vvilling a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> carefull to preſerve tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> advantages, that God h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beſtovved on her, bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by ſome particulars of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diet, and by all oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lavvfull meanes: but ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much deteſted to ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> uſe of anie thing, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvas a fard, or in the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> manner approached of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>And as she could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> chufe but be conſcious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:50564:69"/> herſelfe of thoſe advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, that she poſſeſſed in this, and in other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, and vvas hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie glad of them: ſo she made no other uſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>off, than to thank God for hauing giuen her them; beeing verie farre from taking anie pride or vanitie in them, and from deſpiſing others for vvanting them. And vvhere-as verie fevv vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are handſome in the eyes of thoſe of their ovvne ſexe; it beeing a
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:50564:70"/> verie generall infirmiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in it, ſo to be blinde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvith envious emulatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as either not to ſee at a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe advantages, vvhic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> others doe poſſeſſe in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and other particulars, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſee them vvith grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diminution: (as on t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> contrary verie fevv <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them are deemed oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> than handſome by them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelves, though never ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> farre from it) my Lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvas ſo much of a diff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rent a diſpoſition, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> man could be more f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vourable
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:50564:70"/> in judging of vvomens handſomnes, and of their other good qualities; nor more vvil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and forvvard to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe as much, and vvith greateſt candour to give unto every one, upon all occaſions, the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations they deſerved.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="text">
            <head>XIX.</head>
            <p>She vvas vvonderfull neate about herſelfe, and about her houſe, and a
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:50564:71"/> greate lover of decencie and comelynes about both, loving fine and fashionable apparell well and handſome furniture likevviſe; but neither o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them vvith exceſſe. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> although she vvould hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> taken a verie large ſco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in them, if she vvoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have meerlie follovv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her naturall inclinatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvhich vvould have ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ried her to the utmo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that could have ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvith her purſe and q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litie: yet reaſon and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:50564:71"/> vvere ſo prevalent vvith her, as made her verie much abate of thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and made her much more moderate in them, than moſt other perſons, even ſuch as are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviſe both good and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, vvould have been in the ſame caſe. And every day she grevv viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie to a greater perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in this particular, and to have her heart leſſe and leſſe ſet upon thoſe outvvard orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; often expreſſing
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:50564:72"/> her diſlike of thoſe, who minds beeing altoge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther fixed on the ado<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning and ſetting out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porarie lodgin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and perishable bodie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvhich vvithin a lit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvhile muſt be relinq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>shed, and reduced to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and corruption, have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thoughts of adorni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their ſoules vvith true v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue and pietie, the one<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> true ornaments of ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tians, that are to laſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ever, and to be revvar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> vvith eternall happyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:50564:72"/> and bleſſed immortalitie.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="text">
            <head>XX.</head>
            <p>She vvas a greate lover of truth, and by reaſon there-off did not onelie deteſt all Kind of lyes, eſpeciallie ſuch as vvere any vvayes malicious, or prejudiciall to others, and tended to the detorting and depraving of their ſayings or actions; but vvas vvonderfull exact in keeping her vvord, and in making good her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:50564:73"/> though made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver ſo curſorilie or ſup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficiallie, and that even the ſmalleſt matters, vvell as in thoſe of g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter moment. For vvas fullie perſvvad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that people are as m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bound, both in hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and in conſcience, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>complish a bare and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>luntary promiſe, as a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> formall contract, con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med vvith an oath, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vvith all other bind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g ſolemnities. And as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ever conformed her o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:50564:73"/> practice there-unto, ſo she laboured to induce all others, in vvhom she had anie intereſt, to doe the ſame, and rather to ſuffer any inconvenience, or loſſe, than to find-out a pretext of going from their vvord: repreſenting unto them, as unto her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that one ought to promiſe nothing incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideratelie, but to thinK vvell of it, before one ingage ones ſelfe: but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving once paſſed ones vvord, that then there
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:50564:74"/> remaineth nothing elſe but performance, if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> matter promiſed be lavv<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full and poſſible. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as in all other parts of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> life, ſo in this too, s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> had a ſingular care <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvalking by that gold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rule, to deale ſo vvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> others, as she did deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> to be dealt vvithall h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe. Love to tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> made her alſo verie i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> partiall, not onelie in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> behalfe of ſtrangers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> euen of herſelfe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f all her neereſt relatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:50564:74"/> judging of all vvith the ſame unbiaſſed equitie and equalitie, both in queſtions of intereſt and of concernment, and in thoſe concerning the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of actions, and of qualificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the mind and of the bodie.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="text">
            <head>XXI.</head>
            <p>She vvas extreamlie fearefull of her nature, inſomuch as she vvould figure unto herſelfe and apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d dangers, vvhere there vvas none at all; eſpeciallie upon the vva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:50564:75"/> and not onelie upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſea, vvhere all thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at the beſt appeared veri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> terrible unto her, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon the verie rivers: ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as it vvas death to her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> London, to come into boate, though the vvat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvas never ſo calme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> even here at Paris, in tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> boats uſed upon the Sei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (incomparablie bigg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſurer, than thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Thames) she thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> herſelfe every jot as un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and though she vvo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> novv and then be perſv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:50564:75"/> vvith much adoe, to goe by vvater to Charen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, or to Chaliot, yet her mind vvas at no eaſe nor quiet, as long as she vvas upon the river, even in the faireſt and ſtilleſt vveather. Yet grace and reaſon did ſo overſvvay this her naturall timou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſnes, as notvvhitſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the greate exceſſe of it, there vvas nothing ſo terrible, but she could reſolve to undergoe it, either for the maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a good cauſe, or
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:50564:76"/> anie other vvay called t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it by God; and nothin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo hazardous, but s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> could be induced to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> upon good grounds, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at the appearance of an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neceſſitie, or greate co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>veniencie. This vvas t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> reaſon, that she, vvho <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> trembled and quaked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the leaſt apprehenſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> death, and at the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> shaddovv of anie dang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> though but an imagi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie one, thorough the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cret and ſuddain mori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of her naturall infirm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:50564:76"/> in that particular; could in a ſetled mind think on death, and that under anie shape, vvith as much quietnes of mind, and undauntednes, as more could not be expected of a moſt valourous vvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, or of a man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate in courageous vviſdom. And that this vvas not a deluſion, hath vvell appeared by the effect, she having looked death in the face, vvithout beeing in the leaſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner appalled at it, during
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:50564:77"/> this laſt period of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> life, and ever ſince thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> greate and frequent loſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of blood, vvhich at lengt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have carried her avvay gave her juſt cauſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conceive herſelfe in da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger of it; as she did to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> full, from the beginning<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>For although that aft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> every fit, except the ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> laſt of all, she came ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> verie vvell to herſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> again, (as hath been mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at full declared at t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> entrance of this treati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet ever ſince the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:50564:77"/> them her mind gave her, that she vvould not out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live them, but that aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redlie they vvould make an end of her.</p>
            <p>VVherefore, for to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare me for her death, vvhich she knevv vvould be moſt grievous to me (according to the exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive love I bore her) she vvould often talKe of it, not onelie about the time of thoſe fits, and vvhen she vvas nevvlie come out of them, but even at other times, and farre from
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:50564:78"/> them. And althoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> every foot I vvould fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have hindered her of ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king of it, the thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of looſing her beeing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> unſupportable to me, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I could not indure th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> leaſt mention of it; y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> she vvould ſtill goe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> notvvhitſtanding all n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> oppoſition, and freque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> interruptions, telling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that it vvas good alvvay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to think of the vvor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and that it vvould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver the more, for talKi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of it. Novv the ſum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:50564:78"/> of thoſe her diſcourſes, tending ever to the ſame purpoſe, vvas, That she nothing at all apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded death, but vvas moſt vvilling to undergoe it, if it pleaſed God ſo to diſpoſe of her; finding nothing in it to trouble her, but the thought of the ſorrovv, vvhich that ſeparation vvould cauſe unto me: beſeeching me, if ſo it fell out, to uſe my vvhole ſtrength for to hinder me from ſuccom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing under it, and for to
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:50564:79"/> make me beare that aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ction patientlie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> make this her counſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſink the deeper into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mind, she vvould ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> uſe, as of other conſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rations, ſo of that of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> girle, vvhoſe loſſe vvou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be too greate, if vvith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mother she should al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> come to looſe her fath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and that in a ſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> countrie, farre from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> her friends and kindr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: vvherefore I ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> doe all I could for to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerve me for her<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:50564:79"/> vvas all she ever ſaid of her to me on that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. For knovving full vvell, that next to herſelfe I loved her moſt perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, as much as a child can be beloved by a father; she knew it ſuperfluous to tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke to me, of beeing care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and tender of her, and of making much of her.</p>
            <p>And theſe ſame things (of her finding nothing in her death to trouble her, but the grief it vvould cauſe unto me; vvith the vvonted adjurations, that
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:50564:80"/> I vvould ſtrive to mode<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rate it for Gods ſake, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for her ſake, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerve myſelfe for our gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le) she repeated to me ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verall times in that sho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpace, that vvas betvvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her laſt fit, and her en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the abundance of tear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvhich her imminent d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger, frequent faintin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and greate paines and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſings, drevv from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, giuing her occaſion to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> nevv that counſell ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t unto me, vvhere-off <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ſavv I had ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:50564:80"/> alreadie, and vvould have much more shortlie after. And she continued to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe this chriſtian reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied vvith ſo much tendernes of love tovvards me (of not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending death at all in her ovvn regard, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in mine) to the verie laſt, as long as she vvas able to expreſſe anie thing, and vvhen that she vvas novv at the verie point of death, and had it even vvithin her, and upon her lips. For a little
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:50564:81"/> before she loſt her ſpeec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> after one of her grievo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſt and laſt toſſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vvhen the ſight and ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of vvhat she indured, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the moſt evident ſignes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the inevitablenes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> loſſe, had cauſed me, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tranſport of ſorrovv, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> throvv myſelfe upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bed by her ſide with ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dance of teares, she <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in french (the langu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e she had onelie ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e all that night, beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe that all the perſons in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e room underſtood it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:50564:81"/> moſt of them underſtood no other) <hi>Violà tout le mal,</hi> that is, <hi>Loe there all the euill:</hi> the meaning of vvhich vvords, verie intelligible to me by vvhat ſo often before she had expreſſed more at large unto me, vvas, That she vvas ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or apprehenſive of no ill to herſelfe in her death, but onelie of the evill and grief it did and vvould cauſe unto me. And she ſpoke this thus shortlie, becauſe that ſpeaking be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun novv to be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvhat
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:50564:82"/> troubleſome a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> difficult unto her. Neith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> doe I knovv, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpoke anie thing elſe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> it, but that she gave <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bleſſing to her chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, vvhom she ſavv ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d moſt ſadlie at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s foot (the poore lamb <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the mothers cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o heart much beyond v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at is uſuall in ſo youn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n age) and gave and as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d, vvith ſvveeteſt expre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>s, accompanied vvith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt ſvveet and tender l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s, an aſſurance of of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:50564:82"/> forgivenes of anie diſpleaſure, that at anie time might have been cauſed by the one of us to the other. For after that beeing riſen, for to give the midvvife and the nurce-keeper vvay to change her to another place, as she had deſired: I found, vvhen that vvas done, and that I came again to her, that she had loſt her ſpeech, though not yet her fences. For a meſſe of broth, vvith ſome medcinall thing in
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:50564:83"/> it, vvhich D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sarraſin and the Midvvife judged pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per for her, and deſire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her to take, hauing bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> refuſed by her; as tire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the greate varietie o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cordials and other thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that had been given to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſince the beginning of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> fit, and finding it no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> althogether bootleſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> take anie thing vvha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer: aſſoon as I h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> tendered it unto her, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> prayed her to take it f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> my ſake, she took it ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> readilie, and took-dov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:50564:83"/> every drop of it. And hauing not long after alſo loſt her ſences, she conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in that eſtate the matter of a quarter of an houre longer: and hauing been verie quiet and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me this laſt halfe houre of her life (all her paines and pangs having quite left her, and her toſſings beeing quite ceaſed vvith them) she vvent-out like a candle, and gave-up her ghoſt moſt quietlie: going herſelfe to taKe poſſeſſion of heavenlie
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:50564:84"/> bliſſe, but leaving me f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of moſt grievous a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> mortall ſorrovv, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as long as my dayes; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> beeing nothing on t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s earth, that can make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> unto me that joy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> comfort, vvhich I h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e loſt by looſing her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reſt companie.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="text">
            <head>XXII.</head>
            <p>Her greate reſolut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n againſt death, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> courageous contemt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f all the terrours of it, to
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:50564:84"/> the verie laſt moment; as it vvas altogether contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to her naturall diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo it proceeded vvhollie from divine grounds, and from the gracious aſſiſtaunce of Gods bleſſed ſpirit, quicK<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and ſtrengthening her faith in the mercie of God, thorough the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Chriſts precious blood, and of his bitter death and paſſion: her heart beeing anchored in an unshaken aſſurance on thoſe infallible promiſes
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:50564:85"/> of our bleſſed Saviou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>That vvho-ſo-ever beleeve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.14. &amp; 5.4.24. &amp; 6.51. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>shall not perish, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> have everlaſting life, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> come into condemnation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> paſſe from death unto life, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> live for ever.</hi> VVhich <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> faith she expreſſed f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quentlie, as in for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r times, ſo during theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> laſt moments; eſpecia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e after that the continu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of her bleeding, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than it had been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in anie former fit, her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent faintings, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexitie of the midv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:50564:85"/> and of the reſt of her friends and people about her, their vvhiſpering to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and the ſending-for of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Drelincourt, one of the french Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Charenton, had made her comprehend cleerlie, that she vvas novv come to the laſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod of her life. And having expreſſed greate joy and contentment at the ſight of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Drelin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covrt, it beeing betvvixt eight and nine of the clock vvhen he came; she
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:50564:86"/> preſentlie compoſed he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe for to heare his e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hortation, and to pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvith him. His exhort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion vvas indeed a mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> heavenlie one, the ſum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of it beeing, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> should abſolutelie re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gne herſelfe into t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e hands of God, either f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r life or for death; that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e should caſt herſelfe in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the armes of Chriſt Ieſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, and in his name, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r his merits ſake, aske <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f God forgivenes of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r faults and tranſgreſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:50564:86"/> vvith a certain aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of obtaining it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that bee in reconciled to God by the blood and media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Saviour, death vvas not all to be feared by her, becauſe it vvould be no death to her, but a paſſage from this vale of miſery to life and joy everlaſting: vvith many other moſt excellent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, fitted to her preſent condition, and for to make her quit this life vvith alacritie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and after that follovved the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:50564:87"/> prayer, tending to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſame purpoſes: durin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> both vvhich, though the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvere of a greate length and that her pain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and unquietnes vve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> grovving on her befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they vvere begun, she la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> verie ſtill, giuing grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> attention to them, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> follovving the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all alo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vvith up-lifted hands a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eyes, as likevviſe vvith h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> voice upon all the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> pregna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, paſſages of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. And after that they vv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> done, she aſſured me, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:50564:87"/> her heart too had fullie gone along vvith them from the beginning to the end, and that she had found a greate deale of ſingular comfort and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in them. VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo vvhen that M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Drelincourt, after he had done, vvithdrevv himſelfe into the next roome, for to give vvay to me, to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sarraſin, to the midvvife and keeper, and to the reſt of the vvomen, to come about her, for to give her ſomething, and
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:50564:88"/> to afford her other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſary accommodations she thinking, that he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gone avvay for good an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all, ſent after him, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pray him not to leave he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but to ſtay vvith her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the end, for to renev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unto her from time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> time that ſpirituall co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort, vvhich he had beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo effectuallie to miniſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unto her. And he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ving ſent her vvord, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he had no other inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> came preſentlie back in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the chamber again: a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:50564:88"/> from that time he never quit her to the laſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting her from time to time (as the intermiſſions of her faintings, and of her anguish and toſſings, miniſtred opportunitie) vvith short exhortations, and vvith ejaculatorie prayers; the vvhich vvere ſtill moſt cordiallie recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and follovved by her. And in all thoſe paines and anxieties she never ſpoke an impatie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vvord, but that ſometimes she exclaimed, <hi>Ce jeune coeur
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:50564:89"/> ne ſe veut rendre,</hi> that is, <hi>This young heart vvill not yeeld.</hi> For her heart beeing in its full ſtrength and vigour, as not at all aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by anie ſicknes, ſtruggled hard vvith death, cauſed by meer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> emptynes, and the loſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of blood; vvhich thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alſo she had apprehended she having told you Lordship but the day b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, that as she feare not death at all, ſo th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> paines, vvhich she exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cted to indure before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:50564:89"/> did ſomevvhat terrifie her. Yet neither the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of them, vvhen yet abſent, nor the ſence of them, vvhen she novv ſuffered them, did in the leaſt manner shake her reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and vvillingnes to dye, nor her affiance in the goodnes and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of her Saviour, as not neither her tender care of me: but having continued conſtant in them all, and the Lord hauing done her the grace, to give ner eaſe, and to free her from thoſe
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:50564:90"/> diſquieting paines, before he tooke her avvay, she concluded her life vvith a moſt bleſſed end, to the great edification, yea and admiration, of all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtanders by, even ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvere of a contrary Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Novv, My lord, let a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the vvorld judge vvith yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lordship, vvhether havin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> loſt ſuch a vvife, ſo good, gracious, ſo loving, ſo lovel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo accomplished every vv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and that in the verie flovv
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:50564:90"/> of her age, vvhen she vvas but five and tvventy yeares old; I can grieve moderately; and vvhether my ſorrovv can be juſtlie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned, though verie exceſſive and laſting. I knovv the Lord hath done me no vvrong, in taking her from me, vvho vvas his ovvn, and in uſing that right over her, vvhich he hath over all his creatures, as Souverain Lord and Maſter, vvhereby it is free for him, to dispoſe of them at anie time as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth: and I knovv alſo, that J have given his divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:50564:91" rendition="simple:additions"/> cauſe enough, to ſend me this croſſe, and anie other that I am capable off. But theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſiderations as they are of force for to make me take thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> croſſe at his hands vvithou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> murmuring (the vvhich truſt to have done exactli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not having had the leaſt tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptation of calling his juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into queſtion, for having de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thus vvith me) ſo I find th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not ſufficient for to hinder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of being ſenſible to the full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the evill, that he hath in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cted on me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> neither doe I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leeve, that vvhen he ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:50564:91"/> anie grievous calamitie to his ſervants, he is offended vvith them, for ſeeing their ſorrovv proportionable to the bitternes of vvhat he maketh them ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. For in this verie particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, vvhich is novv my caſe, my vvoefull and deplorable caſe; J find, that vvhen he thought good, in taking from the Prophet Ezechiel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 24.15. &amp; ſeq.</note> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of his eyes <hi>(as he hath done mine from me) to forbid him, for ſome myſterious ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, all outvvard expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of mourning, even the verie shedding of teares: yet
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:50564:92"/> he no vvayes forbid him t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> grieve reallie and invvardlie but rather gave him a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, or at the leaſt an ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſe permiſſion, for doing ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the firſt vvords of the 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> verſe, if they be taken in the right ſenſe, as hath been do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of S. Hierome, and ſome other of the beſt Interpreters. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as for that high degree of her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> call vertue and vviſdome, not onelie not beeing ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deeplie touched vvith a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> croſſe or affliction, though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver ſo bitter and cruell, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> finding even matter of joy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:50564:92"/> it, and of giving God thanks for it: as I admire it in them that poſſeſſe it, ſo I confeſſe to be verie farre from it, and to ſee little ground of hoping ever to attaine to it; especiallie in this particular, vvhich hath lighted upon the tendereſt and leaſt armed part of my ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And my caſe is the more to be pittyed, becauſe that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving loſt in my deareſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort that vvhich J moſt loued, and vvhere-in I moſt joyed in this vvorld, and thereby my life beeing become burdenſom and hatefull to me; yet there
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:50564:93"/> lyeth upon me a cruell neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, not onelie of not abandon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning or vvilfullie neglecting i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (vvhich I vvould not do hovv-ever, becauſe abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie forbidden by him, vvhoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> holie vvill and commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t muſt be the rule of all o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> actions) but even of deſirin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and striving vvith all poſſib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> care to uphold and to prolo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> it, for to preſerve myſelfe f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that deare pledge of our m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall love, vvhich she hath l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me; both becauſe mine ovv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> affection, agreable to the dict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of God and Nature, leade
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:50564:93"/> me stronglie there-unto; and becauſe that that bleſſe ſoule hath in her latter dayes, even to the laſt moments of her life, made it ſo often her moſt ſerious requeſt to me, and her onelie requeſt: the vvhich not to ſeek to fulfill to the utmoſt, as farre as anie vvayes lyeth in my povver (though nothing elſe obliged me to it) I vvould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a crime of the next nature to ſacriledge. So as J muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to live many yeares yet, if God ſo ſee it fitting, yea and vvish and indeavour to doe ſo, though all the ſvveetnes of
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:50564:94"/> my life be taken from me, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that I ſee nothing but thic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> clouds of diſmall draknes befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me; vvhich make death unt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me, as to myſelfe, infiniteli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> preferable before life. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> even the memorie of her ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tues, as on the one ſide it mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtreth ſome kind of contentm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and comfort to me, especiall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vvhen I conſider the bleſſe revvard there-off, vvhich sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> novv reapeth in heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the preſence of God she in joyeth the fulnes of joy, all te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res beeing vviped-off from h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> eyes: ſo on the other ſide it do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:50564:94"/> mainlie aggravate my ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rovv, becauſe that the greater they vvere, and the reſt of her moſt deſireable and lovelie qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, the greater is my loſſe, in beeing deprived of her. But be her deareſt Jdea matter of comfort to me, or matter of ſorrovv, it shall ever and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantlie be preſent to my ſoule, and therein to the end of my dayes take-up that vvhole roome, vvhich a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, vvithout offence to his Creatour and Saviour, and vvith a due ſub-ordination to that love, vvhich is ovving
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:50564:95" rendition="simple:additions"/> to him in the firſt place, ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lavvfullie afford to anie thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> created; juſt in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as she did poſſeſſe it duri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that time, that J vvas bleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vvith that greate happyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of injoying her moſt amia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> companie. I should nev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have done, My lord, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vvould take that ſcope <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dvvelling on this theam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, vvhich my affection and gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>f doth prompt unto me. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> feare of importuning y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r Lordship conſtraineth m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> breake off: and ſo vvith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y moſt heartie thanks for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:50564:95"/> thoſe friendlie and pious pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, vvhich ever ſince this fatall blovv you have taken, and doe still take daylie, in endeavouring to heale this deep and incurable vvound, and to miniſter all spirituall comfort to me, I reamaine</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordships moſt obliged and humble, but deſolate and diſconſolate ſervant, ARNOLD BOATE.</signed>
               <dateline>Paris <date>this 24. of May 1651.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50564:96"/>
            <p>D. O. M. S. LECTISSIMAE FOE MINAE MARGARITAE DVNGAN: ANIMI PIETATE ET PROBITATE; AMORE AC FIDE IN DEV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> PVRIORIS RELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GIONIS ZELO, CHARITATE IN PROXIMO<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> PHILOSTORGIA IN MA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>TVM, LIBEROS, PARENTE<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> MODESTIA, CASTITAT<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> BENIGNITATE, LIBER<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>LITATE, COMITAT<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> EXIMIE ORNATAE: ETIAM IVSTITIAE <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> VERITATIS AMOR<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> PRVDENTIA; GEN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ROSITATE; RELIQVIS VIRTVTIB<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, SVPRA SEXVM ET ANN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, PRAEFVLGENTI: INDOLIS QVOQVE ET <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GENII FOELICITA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; FORMAE PRAESTANT<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>A, ET VENVSTATE,
<pb facs="tcp:50564:96"/> ORIS-QVE DECORE ET GRATIA; MORVM SINGVLARI SVA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VITATE, ET ELEGANTIA; VNICE CONSPICVAE: VXORI TOT NOMINIBVS SIBI CHARISSIMAE: MOESTISSIMVS MARITVS ARNOLDVS BOOTIVS; IN IPSO IVVENTAE FLORE, CVM TANTVM 25. AETATIS ANNVM AGERET, SIBI EREPTAM, 17. APRILIS 1651. IN CONSOLABILI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER LVGENS; POSVIT HOC MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NVMENTVM AMORIS EXIMII, ET INDIVIDVI, ATQVE AD SVPREMAM DIEM EODEM TENORE DV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RATVRI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50564:97"/>
            <head>Lectiſſimam Matronam, &amp; ſibi ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſſimam, Margaritam Dung<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nam, D. Arnoldi Bootij, ſibi etia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> amiciſſimi, Coniugem, verè fle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deflebat ſibi morte ademtam, eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ex tempore carmine, Th. Sinſerſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Candidae Caſae apud Scotos Epiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> pus indigniſsimus:</head>
            <l>
               <hi>VERE Debemus morti nos noſtraque,</hi> V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>Ignarus cauſae, dixerat ille nimis.</l>
            <l>Quod ſaepe expertus, iam ſentio, dum mibi cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>Dunganam, ab nimiùm mors violenta rapit.</l>
            <l>Mors violenta rapit Dunganam in flore iuveni</l>
            <l>Prae cunctis alijs quae mihi chara fuit.</l>
            <l>Sed mihi ſolamen, quod Vati non fuit illi, eſt</l>
            <l>Spes, quod per Chriſtum vita redibit ei.</l>
            <l>Sic eſt, peccatum morti nos ſubjicit omnes:</l>
            <l>Chriſtus at ex ipſa morte redemtor erit.</l>
            <l>Sic tibi, ſic certò fiet, Dungana, beata</l>
            <l>In Christo moriens, dum tibi vera fides.</l>
            <l>Vera &amp; viva fides; quae vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> expreſſa per om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>Morte etiam in media te comitata fuit.</l>
            <l>Hanc quoque tu in mente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> revoca, chariſſime <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>Quae fuit erepta in conjuge viva fides:</l>
            <l>Ereptae quae tanta premit, ne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eopprimatorbu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>Moeſtitia. In viva coniuge, viva fides</l>
            <l>Vitam animae in coelo poſt mortem praeſtat: ean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>Corporeae parti reddet &amp; illa ſuae.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:50564:97"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
